Ernestine Gilbreth Carey Papers, 1915-2005
Sophia Smith Collection
Ernestine Gilbreth Carey papers
1915-2005
Carey, Ernestine Gilbreth
28
89 boxes (48.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This collection is comprised of materials relating to the personal and professional life of Ernestine Gilbreth Carey, author of Cheaper by the Dozen, Belles on their Toes, and other novels. Carey was a fervent supporter of public libraries, active in the anti-censorship group, Right to Read, Inc., and a Smith College trustee from 1967 to 1972.
Ernestine Moller Gilbreth was born in New York City on April 5, 1908. She was the daughter of Frank B. and Lillian (Moller) Gilbreth, early scientific management experts. The third oldest of twelve children (eleven of whom lived to adulthood), Ernestine grew up in Montclair, New Jersey, in an unconventional household. In 1949 she and her younger brother Frank B. Gilbreth, Jr. parlayed their childhood memories of efficiency experiments, in which the children were the guinea pigs, into the best-selling novel Cheaper by the Dozen. The sequel, Belles on Their Toes (1951), picks up where its predecessor ended-with Frank, Sr., suffering a fatal heart attack on the eve of Ernestine's high school graduation.
Frank Gilbreth's sudden death delayed Ernestine's college plans by a year, as the family's finances dictated that her mother return to work immediately, carrying on the work she and her husband did as industrial/management consultants. Ernestine would nonetheless graduate from Smith College as an English major in 1929. The following year she found work as a buyer for Macy's Department store in New York City and, on September 13, 1930, she married Charles ("Chick") Everett Carey, a salesman for the Sperry Rand Corporation. Unlike Ernestine's prolific parents, the Careys had only two children, spaced well apart. Lillian (known as Jill) was born October 28, 1938, and Charles, Jr. (Charlie) was born December 5, 1942. Both of her children were born in New York City and, very much like Ernestine's mother, Carey returned to work soon after each child was born. She remained a buyer at Macy's until 1944, when the family moved to Manhasset on Long Island. Carey immersed herself in the community and spent more time with her children, but soon realized she needed something more to do and began writing, drafting a "fact-based" draft of a novel about her childhood.
When her brother Frank, Jr. returned from service in World War II and was having a rough re-entry to civilian life, their mother suggested that Ernestine share the novel with her brother, who had returned to his pre-war profession of journalism. He tightened the prose and injected more humor. Cheaper by the Dozen was published in 1949 and made into a popular movie the next year. The sequel, Belles on Their Toes, would also be made into a movie, though it never enjoyed the popularity of Cheaper by the Dozen, which is still read by school children decades after its publication. Because they had shared their stories-and their lives-in the successful novels, Ernestine and Frank, Jr. decided to share evenly amongst their siblings and their mother all royalties from both books and the movies based on them.
Ernestine (Gilbreth) Carey would go on to publish three more novels during the 1950s, all semi-autobiographical: Jumping Jupiter (1952), Rings around Us (1956), and Giddy Moment (1958), though none of them would come close to the popularity of Cheaper by the Dozen. Thereafter Carey's career as a writer stalled and she was never able to find a publisher for her last two novels, As Silver is Tried (1960s) and Razzle Dazzle (1970s). After her mother died in 1972, Carey became the primary family historian, especially interested in securing the legacy of her two parents, particularly that of her mother whose impressive career as an engineer spanned more than four decades after the death of Carey's father. From the 1970s until shortly before her death in 2006, Carey researched and wrote multiple drafts of various versions of biographical treatments of both her parents and her mother. However, she was unable to find an interested publisher.
In addition to her career as an author, Carey was active in the anti-censorship group, Right to Read, Inc., and was a fervent supporter of public libraries, serving as a trustee for the Manhasset Public Library during the 1950s until the family moved to Arizona in 1959. During the 1950s and early 1960s, Carey enjoyed a moderately successful career as a speaker, especially for women's clubs and local libraries. She based most of her talks on her main interests: her family and the "right to read" anything one wanted. Ernestine Gilbreth Carey was also an active alumna, holding office in her local Smith College clubs both on Long Island and in Phoenix. She was a Smith College trustee from 1967 to 1972.
Ernestine Gilbreth Carey died in Fresno, California, on November 4, 2006.
The Ernestine Gilbreth Carey Papers consist of 48.25 linear feet and are related to both her professional and private life, as well as to the lives and work of her parents, particularly her mother. Types of materials include correspondence, diaries, manuscripts, photographs, journal and newspaper articles, and memorabilia. The papers are arranged in eight series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. CORRESPONDENCE
III. WRITINGS
IV. SPEECHES AND APPEARANCES
V. SUBJECT FILES
VI. LILLIAN MOLLER GILBRETH AND FRANK BUNKER GILBRETH, SR.
VII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
VIII. MEMORABILIA
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The bulk of the materials relate to Carey's various research and writing projects and date from the late 1950s to 2004.
Carey's papers and their idiosyncratic arrangement reveal a deep interest in systems for information management, as well as experimentation with filing systems to facilitate her own access to the extensive documentation she acquired and generated.
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Ernestine Gilbreth Carey donated her Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection beginning in 1965. The final accession arrived in 2007.
Cheaper by the Dozen--Sources; Authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Censorship--United States--20th century; Family--United States--History--20th century-Sources; Carey, Ernestine Gilbreth; Gilbreth, Frank B. (Frank Bunker), 1911-2001; Gilbreth family; Smith College. Board of Trustees; Gilbreth, Lillian Moller, 1878-1972; Gilbreth, Frank B. (Frank Bunker), 1868-1924
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1929-2003, 2.5 linear ft
  This series provides an overview of Ernestine Carey's life and includes articles about her and her family; financial, legal, and property records; and awards. Also of interest is the material regarding the birth of her two children which includes notes, hospital literature, and memorabilia.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1915-2005, 20 linear ft.
  This series is organized into three subseries: Family, Friends and associates, and General. The Family correspondence is especially interesting, providing a window onto the dynamics among "the Dozen" as they called themselves. They often wrote group letters or asked the recipient to share a letter with another sibling. In addition to her own two adult children and their families, Ernestine Carey was also close to several of her nieces and nephews, as reflected by the correspondence. Among the Friends and associates, most notable is long-time friend Ruth Cowell, a Manhasset, New York librarian. In keeping with Carey's filing system, the General correspondence is divided into the following sections: Organizations, Publishers and agents, International, and Alphabetical. Many of the folders contain notes, publications, and research materials in addition to correspondence. The General correspondence reflects Carey's many years of research for her proposed biography of her parents as well as her dealings with publishers and agents.
- SERIES III. WRITINGS 1923-2003, 8.5 linear ft.
  This series includes both published and unpublished materials and has been arranged in the following subseries: Books; Diaries/autobiographical; Drafts, fragments and notes; and Miscellaneous. It is in this series that one can best see a writer at work. The Diaries/Autobiographical subseries contains Carey's thoughts on a variety of topics and reveals a rather complex woman who wrestled with family concerns, aging and a changing world as the 1960s rolled into the 1970s. Among the Books are two unpublished novels; it appears that Carey worked on "As Silver is Tried" during the first half of the 1960s decade and "Razzle Dazzle" during the mid-1970s. The former was meant to be a medical thriller and the latter another autobiographical treatment of the Carey family. Within the Cheaper by the Dozen sub-subseries, the fan mail, particularly from children, over the decades, is a testament to the enduring popularity of this book. The Drafts, fragments, and notes subseries has been divided into "titled" or "untitled," and illuminates Carey's various interests. Miscellaneous materials include book reviews, royalty statements, publication contracts and miscellaneous notes.
- SERIES IV. SPEECHES AND APPEARANCES, 1 linear ft.
  This series contains speeches, speech notes, contracts and correspondence related to Carey's speaking engagements.
  This series has not been fully processed and may be difficult to use.
- SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES, 4.25 linear feet
  Materials in this series reflect Carey's varied interests. While this series has not been fully processed and may be difficult to use, it has been loosely organized as follows: Cartoons, Censorship, Family Genealogy, Inventions, Smith College, and Travel. Materials include notes, research materials, clippings, correspondence, memorabilia, and publications.
- SERIES VI. LILLIAN MOLLER GILBRETH AND FRANK B. GILBRETH, SR., 3.75 linear feet
  This series contains material by and about the Gilbreths collected by their daughter over many years. Included are research notes, correspondence, clippings, publications, and drafts.
- SERIES VII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS, 4 linear feet
  Included are photographic prints, a few glass plate negatives, and albums primarily containing travel photographs. Of particular interest are photographs of the Gilbreth family during Ernestine's childhood.
  The majority of the audiovisual materials are audiocassette tapes. These appear to be primarily Carey's dictation of diary entries, correspondence, and research on Lillian Moller Gilbreth and Frank B. Gilbreth, Sr. Notes attached to the cassettes indicate that most were transcribed. Also included are recordings of speeches and appearances by Carey. There are also a few reel-to-reel audiotapes and a small number of VHS video recordings.
- SERIES VIII. MEMORABILIA, 3 linear feet
  This series primarily consists of scrapbooks and some memorabilia.
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address books (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
  - Articles about EGC and her family, 1930-2006, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-12)
  - Articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 12a)
  - Awards, plaques and certificates (Box 1)
    - Arizona State Reading Council, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Friends of the Phoenix Public Library, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Who's Who, 1979-95 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1994-98, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Biographical statements, 1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Calendars and schedules, 1939-99 (with gaps) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Charles E. Carey, Sr., 1965-87 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Children, 1938-42, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Church, 1938-2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Employees, 1993-2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Events, 1950-75, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Financial/legal (Box 2)
    - Business expenses, 1954-58 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Disbursement of estate, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Certificates and government identification, 1929-82 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Living trust, 1974-75 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Merrill Lynch, 1989-92 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous expenses and receipts, 1951-98 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
    - Moving expenses, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Macy's pay stubs, 1937-44 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Postal expenses, 1987-88 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Power of attorney, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Property (Box 3)
    - Munsey Park (Manhasset), New York, 1944-59 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - Westhampton Beach, New York, 1950-79 (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
  - Scottsdale, Arizona, 1959, 1986-91 (Box 15-16)
    - Rainbow Valley land deal, 1960-89 (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
    - Wills and related documents, 1957-90 (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
    - Wills and related documents, 1957-90 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Health related documents, 1938-97 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Membership cards, 1951-2003 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Parties and weddings, 1930-87 (Box 5, Folder 8-11)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Family (Box 5)
    - Barley, Lillian Gilbreth (Carey) Clark and family, 1966-2000 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Barney, Anne (Gilbreth), 1951-82 (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
    - Carey, Charles E., Sr. and Ernestine (Gilbreth) Carey, 1929-85 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
    - Carey, Charles E., Jr. and family, 1952-2003 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
    - Carey family, other, 1938, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Cross, Anne Gilbreth, 1925-29 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Gilbreth, Daniel, 1928-2002 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
    - Gilbreth, Frank B., Jr., 1947-2001 (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
    - Gilbreth, Frederick, 1958-2001 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Gilbreth, John, 1942-2002 (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
    - Gilbreth, Lillian Moller, 1927-68 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Gilbreth, Martha Bunker, 1908 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Gilbreth, Robert, 1957-2002 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Gilbreth, William, 1949-88 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Gilbreth nieces and nephews, 1967-2003 (Box 9, Folder 3-6)
    - Gilbreth group correspondence, 1954-2003 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
    - Heppes, Jane (Gilbreth), 1954-2003 (Box 10, Folder 4-6)
    - Johnson, Lillian (Gilbreth), 1949-2001 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Johnson, Lillian (Gilbreth), 1949-2001 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Moller, Elinor, 1956-69 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Moller family, other, 1938-92 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Tallman, Martha (Gilbreth), 1929-67 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Cousins (Box 11)
      - Bell, Winifred Brown, 1972-84 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Bruckl, Juliana, 1987-88 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Cross, Carol Hasty, 1949-69 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Galbraith, Archibald, 1958-85 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Moller, Frank and Dolly, 1969-94 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Weston, Nancy1971-2001 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Other, 1956-90 (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - Unidentified, 1968-76 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Friends and family, topical (Box 11)
    - Birth of Lillian Gilbreth Carey, 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    - Birth of Charles E. Carey, Jr., 1942 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Death of Charles E. Carey, Sr., 1986 (Box 12, Folder 4-7)
- Friends and associates (Box 12)
  - Individuals (Box 12)
    - Acri, Elaine, 2000-undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Anderson, Charles and Mary, 1982-87 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Basinger, Anne Lloyd, 1928-79 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Bokun, Fanny Butcher, 1963-87 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Butler, Effie, 1980-94 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Callahan, Jane, 1966-76 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Clark, Pearl, 1954-56 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Cowell, Ruth, 1958-94 (Box 13, Folder 8-10)
    - Cowell, Ruth, 1958-94 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - Duffy, Janet, 1989-97 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Dunham, Elizabeth, 1969-93 (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
    - Ertmoed, Kathy, 2001-03 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Hathaway, Lu and Nat, 1990-2002 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Howland, Rosemary, 1968-86 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Krider, "Pete," 1973-86 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Merry, Catherine Simonson, 1976-93 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Mock, Greta C., 1997 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Paul, Lynn, 1992-93 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Smith, Charles Gaston, Jr., 1942-58 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Stevenson, Kit and Doug, 1990-2001 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Tozier, Price, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Wilde, Anne and Richard, 1972-96 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - General, A-Z, 1938-2003 (Box 15-15a, Folder 1-23)
    These folders are mostly unsorted.
- General (Box 15)
  - Organizations (Box 15)
    - American Women's Association, 1978-79 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Business and Profession Women's Club, 1971-83 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Feminist Press, City University of New York, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Engineering Honor Society, Tau Beta Pi, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Engineering Today, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Industrial Engineering Honor Society, 1972-81 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - International Academy of Management, 1979-84 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - International Association for Personnel Women, 1981-87 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - International Federation of University Women, 1983-84 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Institute of Management Services (Box 16)
      - Aronson, Arthur, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Atkins, Margaret, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Institute of Industrial Engineers [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 16)
      - Balestrero, Greg, 1985-93 (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - Beldon, David, 1978-86 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - General, 1985-94 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - Jericho, Jack, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 15)
      - Malcolm, Donald, 1971-86 (Box 16, Folder 16)
      - Nutt, Merle, 1970-71 (Box 16, Folder 17)
      - Radway, Connie, 1982-84 (Box 16, Folder 18)
      - Wolbrink, Jim, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - Zaken, Lisa, 1978-93 (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous, 1958-88 (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - National Academy of Engineering, 1965-82 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - National Society of Professional Engineers, 1981-94 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - National Women's Hall of Fame, 1995 (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - National Women's History Project, 1994-96 (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Society for the Advancement of Management (Box 16)
      - General, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1931-90 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Gilbreth House, 1964-96 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Society of Women Engineers (SWE) (Box 17)
      - General, 1966-96 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Gilbreth Scholarship, 1969-72 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Eaves, Elsie, 1979-81 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Harrod, B.J., 1989-95 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Hicks, Bea, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Loring, Paula, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Martin, Alice, 1979, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Murray-Lenthall, Evelyn, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Peden, Irene, 1965-81 (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Pressman, Ada, 1980-81 (Box 17, Folder 13)
      - Pritchard, Margaret, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 14)
      - Salembier, Olive, 1970-80 (Box 17, Folder 15)
      - Wells, Paula, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Publishers and agents (Box 17)
    - Annie Laurie Williams, Inc., 1949-54 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Authors Guild, 1958-92 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Authors League of America, 1954-58 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Bart, Andrews, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Crain, Maurice, 1953-57 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Crain, Williams, and Sullivan, 1954-85, undated (Box 18, Folder 6-8)
    - Cromwell, Thomas Y., 1949-80 (Box 18, Folder 9-10)
    - Curtis Brown, Ltd., 1966 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - DeLane, Isaak, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Dramatists Guild, 1964-82 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Dramatic Publishing Company, 1961-92, n.d (Box 19, Folder 1-4)
    - Follet Publishing, 1966-70 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Gould, Betsy, 1990-91 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Harper Collins, 1960-91 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Harper & Row, 1976-92 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - John Hochmann Books, 1977-79 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Horch, Franz J., 1950-56 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Jackson, Phyllis, 1974-83 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - James Brown Associates (Box 20)
      - "Rings Around Us," 1954-56 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1944-63 (Box 20, Folder 3-9)
    - Little, Brown and Company, 1950-62 (Box 20, Folder 10-11)
    - Lang Publishing Co., 1993 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Literary agents, 1988-93 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Literary agents- Proposals, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Melanie Jackson Agency, 1982 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - McIntosh and Otis, undated-1985 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - McIntosh and Otis, 1986-93 (Box 21, Folder 2-3)
    - Miscellaneous publishers, 1950-1952 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Putnam Publishing, 1995 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Ricciardi, Michael, 1985 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Rogers, David, 1961-81 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Scott Foresman and Company, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Stern & Reubens, 1949 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Sterling Lord Agency, 1966-73 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Tarq, Rosalyn, 1971-93 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Whitman Publishing, 1958-74 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - International (Box 21)
    - Australia/New Zealand, Sir Walter and Dorothy Scott, 1969-85 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Australia, Urwick, Lyndale F., 1972 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Belgium, 1961-92 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Brabec, Ingrid F., 1978 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Canada, 1969-81 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - CECIOS (European Council of Management), 1984 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - CIOS (World Council of Management) (Box 22)
      - Limp, W., 1982-89 (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - General correspondence, 1977-85 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Denmark: Dvorak International Federation, 1983-88 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - England (Box 22)
      - General, 1982 (Box 22, Folder 10)
      - Dudley, N.A., University of Birmingham, 1974 (Box 22, Folder 11)
      - Fawcett, Nancy, 1975-92 (Box 22, Folder 12)
      - Goreham, Barbara 1982-92 (Box 22, Folder 13)
      - Horn, Jack, 1993 (Box 22, Folder 14)
      - Institute of Management Services, 1977-95 (Box 22, Folder 15)
      - Secar, Nancy, 1985 (Box 22, Folder 16)
      - Shaw, Anne (Box 22, Folder 17)
      - University of London Library, 1982-85 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Whincup, Ernest, 1982 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - France, 1978-83 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Germany (Box 23)
      - General, 1968-98 (Box 23, Folder 4-5)
      - Baer, Esther, 1955-79 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - Bolton, Heidi, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - Henry, Ruth, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 8)
      - Bullinger, Hans-Jorge, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - Landesmuseum fur Technik und Arbeit, 1994-95 (Box 23, Folder 10)
      - Mauel, Ing, 1956-81 (Box 23, Folder 11)
      - Mittelsten-Scheid, Erich, 1965-80 (Box 23, Folder 12)
      - Kruger, Kurt, 1981-83 (Box 23, Folder 13)
      - Mayer-Ball, Edith, 1965-82 (Box 23, Folder 14)
      - Hackstein, Ing Rolf, 1981-88 (Box 23, Folder 15)
      - Ibielski, Dieter, 1981-82 (Box 23, Folder 16)
      - Kloubert, Bruno, 1992-93 (Box 23, Folder 17)
      - DeHaan, Hugo, 1950-79 (Box 23, Folder 18)
      - Rohn, Walter, 1972-83 (Box 23, Folder 19)
      - Saldorf & Witte, 1915-94 (Box 23, Folder 20)
      - Shafer, Suzanne, 1993-95 (Box 23, Folder 21)
      - Scheuchzer, Roland, 1979-84 (Box 23, Folder 22)
      - Von Below, Ing Fritz, 1983 (Box 23, Folder 23)
      - Wimmer, Toni, 1988-92 (Box 23, Folder 24)
    - Greece, 1969-84 (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - Holland, 1923-84 (Box 23, Folder 26)
    - India, 1964-82 (Box 23, Folder 27)
    - Italy, 1994 (Box 23, Folder 28)
    - Japan (Box 23)
      - General, 1996-2003 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - William Jaffe Japanese Correspondence, 1972-87 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - Kadota, Takeji, 1992 (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - Kato, Takeo, 1970-81 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - Narasaki, Kiyoo, 1987-89 (Box 24, Folder 5)
      - Sakamoto, Kiyoshi, 1991 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Waseda University, 1963-87 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Ueno, Ichiro, 1973-95 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous countries, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Norway, 1980-86 (Box 24, Folder 10)